<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Observations upon the Provinces United. And on the state of France. Written by Sr Thomas Overbury.</title>
            <title>Sir Thomas Overbury his observations in his travailes upon the state of the Xvii. Provinces as they stood anno Dom. 1609.</title>
            <author>Overbury, Thomas, Sir, 1581-1613.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O609</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1317_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203062</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863150</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115334</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90222)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115334)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 176:E1317[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Observations upon the Provinces United. And on the state of France. Written by Sr Thomas Overbury.</title>
                  <title>Sir Thomas Overbury his observations in his travailes upon the state of the Xvii. Provinces as they stood anno Dom. 1609.</title>
                  <author>Overbury, Thomas, Sir, 1581-1613.</author>
                  <author>Pass, Simon van de, 1595?-1647, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 80 p. : port. (metal cut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Maxey for Richard Marriot, and are to be sold at his shop in S. Dunstan's Church-yard, Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651 [i.e. 1650]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The portrait of the author is signed: SP excudit SP fe., i.e. Simon Pass.</note>
                  <note>Originally published in 1626 as: Sir Thomas Overbury his observations in his travailes upon the state of the Xvii. Provinces as they stood anno Dom. 1609.</note>
                  <note>Thomason received his copy in December 1650.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 17 1650"; 1 in imprint date crossed through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  Politics and government --  1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Politics and government --  Henry IV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:115334:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:115334:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>THE LIVELY PORTRAICTURE OF SIR THOMAS OVERBURY</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Sir Thomas Overbury</figDesc>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A mans' best fortune or his worst's a wife:</l>
                     <l>Yet I, that knew nor mariage peace nor strife,</l>
                     <l>Live by a good, by a bad one lost my life.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A wife like her I writ, man ſcarſe can wed:</l>
                     <l>Of a false friend like mine, man ſcarſe hath read.</l>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115334:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OBSERVATIONS Upon the PROVINCES UNITED.</p>
            <p>And On the STATE OF FRANCE.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN By S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Overbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. Maxey</hi> for <hi>Richard Marriot,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in S. <hi>Dunſtan's</hi> Church-yard, <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115334:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115334:3"/>
            <head>OBSERVATIONS Upon the PROVINCES UNITED.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this STATE, all things did moſt nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly concurr for the Riſing and Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of it; the diſpoſition
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115334:4"/>of the people being, as muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, ſo induſtrious and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall. The Nature of the Countrey every where Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiable with water; the Situ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of it, having behinde them the <hi>Baltique</hi> Sea, which yeelds them all materials for Ships, and many other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities: and for Men, hard before them <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> both fearing the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Greatneſs; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both concurring for their Aid: the remoteneſſe of their Maſter from them; the Change of Reilgion fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out about the time of their Revolt; and now the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115334:4"/>Marquis of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> a Proteſtant, like to become Duke of <hi>Cleve.</hi> The diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments of the <hi>Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries</hi> did firſt appear ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the going away of the Kings of <hi>Spain,</hi> while the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe of <hi>Parma</hi> Governed; to ſuppreſſe which beginnings, the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> being ſent, inflamed them more, upon attempting to bring in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition and Spaniſh Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, upon the beheading Count <hi>Horne,</hi> and Count <hi>Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> perſecuting thoſe of the Religion, and undertaking to build Cittadels upon all their Towns, which he effected at
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115334:5"/>
               <hi>Antwerp;</hi> but enterprising the like at <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> that Towne revolted firſt, and under it began the War.</p>
            <p>But the more generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt of the Provinces hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened after the death of <hi>Don</hi> LEVVIS <hi>de Requieſens,</hi> and upon the coming down of <hi>Don</hi> JOHN of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> when all the Provinces, excepting <hi>Luxenburgh,</hi> upon the lack of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and other Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, proclaimed the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards Rebels, and enemies to the King: yet the abju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their obedience from the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> was not in a yeer or two after.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115334:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> upon their firſt ſtanding out, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the Soveraigntie of themſelves to ELISABETH Queen of <hi>England,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Protection: both which ſhee neglected, and that while the French ſent greater Aid, and more men of Quality then we: But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Civill Warr began in <hi>France,</hi> that kept them buſie at home; and then the Queen, ſeeing the neceſſitie of being ſupported, upon the pawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Brill</hi> and <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> ſent Money and Men: And after that, moſt part of the great Exploits there were done by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115334:6"/>the Engliſh, who were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the third part of the Army, being four Regiments, beſides eleven hundred in <hi>Fluſhing</hi> and the <hi>Ramekins,</hi> and five hundred in the <hi>Brill.</hi> But of late the King of <hi>France</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing more for them then ours, and paying himſelf the French that were there, they gave equal, if not more coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to that Nation. But upon theſe two Kings they made their whole Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancie; and though with more reſpect to him that was ſtronger for the time; yet ſo as it might give no diſtaſte unto the other.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115334:6"/>
            <p>For the manner of their Government: They have, upon occaſion, an Aſſembly of the Generall States, like our Parliament, being compoſed of thoſe which are ſent from every Province upon Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; and what theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act ſtands for Law. Then is there beſides, a Councell of State, reſiding for the moſt part at the <hi>Hague,</hi> which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends daily occaſions, being rather imployed upon affairs of State, then of particular Juſtice. The moſt potent in this Councel was BARNA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VILL, by reaſon of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates with <hi>Holland.</hi> And
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115334:7"/>beſides both theſe, every Province and great Towne have particular Councels of their own. To all which Aſſemblies, as well of the Generall States, as the reſt, the Gentrie is called for Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſake; but the State in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is Democraticall, the Merchant and the Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man being predominant, the Gentry now but few, and poor; and even at the beginning, the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> ſaw it ſafer to relie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Towns then them: Neither are the Gentrie ſo much engaged in the Cauſe; the People having more Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115334:7"/>in a Free State, they in a Monarchie. Their care in Government is very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act and particular, by reaſon that every one hath an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Intereſt in the State: Such is the equalitie of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, that it renders every man ſatisfied: Such the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Regularity, as a man may ſee, their Lawes were made to guide, not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap: Such their exactneſſe in caſting the expence of an Armie, as that it ſhalt be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually far from Superfluitie and Want; and as much or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and certainty in their Acts of War, as in ours of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115334:8"/>Peace, teaching it to be both Civill, and Rich: And they ſtill retaine that ſigne of a Common-wealth uncorrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, PRIVATE POVERTY, <hi>and</hi> PUBLICK WEALE: For no one private man there is exceeding rich, and few very poor, and no State more ſumptuous in all Publick things.</p>
            <p>But the Queſtion is, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this, being a Free State, will aſwell ſubſiſt in Peace, as it hath done hitherto in Warr; Peace leaving every one to attend his particular wealth; when Fear, while the Warr laſts, maketh them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115334:8"/>concurre for their common ſafety; And <hi>Zealand,</hi> upon the leaſt ſecurity, hath ever been envious at the Predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Utrick,</hi> ready to Mutinie for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: and beſides, it is a doubt, whether the ſame care and ſincerity would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, if they were at their Conſiſtence, as appears yet whiles they are but in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. The Revenue of this State ariſeth chiefely from the Earle of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land's</hi> Demains, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated Church Livings, the riſing and falling of Money, which they uſe with much
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115334:9"/>advantage, their Fiſhing upon our Coaſts, and thoſe of <hi>Norway,</hi> Contribution out of the Enemies Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Taxes upon all things at home, and Impoſitions upon all Merchandises from abroad. Their expences up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an their Ambaſſadors, their Shippings, their Ditches, their Rampiers and Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and commonly they have in pay by Sea and Land 60000 men.</p>
            <p>For their ſtrength; The nature of the Country makes them able to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves long by land, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could any thing have
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115334:9"/>endangered them ſo much as the laſt great Froſt, had not the Treaty been then on foot; becauſe the Enemy beeing then Maſter of the Field, that rendred their Ditches, Marſhes, and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers as firm ground.</p>
            <p>There belongs to that STATE 20000. Veſſells of all ſorts, ſo that if the <hi>Spaniard</hi> were entirely beaten out of thoſe parts, the Kings of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> would take as much paines to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, as ever they did to raiſe them: For being our Enemies, they are able to give us the Law at Sea, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115334:10"/>eate us out of all trade, much more the <hi>French,</hi> having at this time three Ships for our one, though none ſo good as our beſt.</p>
            <p>Now that whereupon the moſt part of their Revenue and ſtrength depends, is their Traffick, in which Myſtery of STATE they are at this day the wiſeſt; for all the Commodities that this part of the world wants, and the <hi>Indies</hi> have, as Spice, Silke, Jewels, Gold, they are become the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyers of them for the reſt of Chriſtendome, except us, as the <hi>Venetians</hi> were of old;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115334:10"/>And all thoſe Commodities that thoſe Northern Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries abound with, and theſe Southerne ſtand in need of, they likewiſe convey thither, which was the ancient Trade of the Eaſterlings: And this they do, having lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to export of their own, by buying of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Countreys the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and ſelling them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine what they bring back at their own prices, and ſo conſequently live upon the idleneſſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And to this purpoſe their Situation ſerves fitly; for the Rivers of the <hi>Rhene,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115334:11"/>the <hi>Maze,</hi> and <hi>Skeld</hi> end all in their Dominions; and the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea lies not farre from them: All which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords them what ever the great Continent of <hi>Germany, Ruſsia,</hi> and <hi>Poland</hi> yeelds; then they again lying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Germany</hi> and the Sea, doe furniſh it backe with all Commodities forraign.</p>
            <p>To remember ſome pieces of their Diſcipline as pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of the reſt; The Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches at night are never all of one Nation, ſo that they can hardly concurre to give up any one Towne. The Commiſſaries are no where
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115334:11"/>ſo ſtrict upon Muſters; and where he finds a Company, thither he reduceth them: ſo that when an Army mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, the Liſt and the Poll are never farre diſagreeing. Their Army is ever well Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, well Armed, and had never yet occaſion to muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for Pay or Victnalls. The Souldiers commit no where fewer Inſolencies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Burgers, fewer Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries upon the Country, nor the Officers fewer deceits upon the Souldiers. And laſtly they provide well that their Generall ſhall have ſmall meanes to invade their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115334:12"/>Liberties: For firſt, their Army is compoſed of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Nations, which have their ſeverall Commanders, and the Commands are diſpoſed by the <hi>STATES</hi> Themſelves, not by the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. And ſecondly, Hee hath never an implicite Commiſſion left to diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but by reaſon their Countrie hath no great bounds, receives daily Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands what to doe.</p>
            <p>Their Territory contains ſix entire Provinces; <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Zealand, Utrick, Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningen, Overiſcell,</hi> and <hi>Friez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115334:12"/>beſides three parts of <hi>Gelderland,</hi> and certaine Towns in <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;</hi> the ground of which is, for the moſt part, fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; the Towns no where ſo equally beautifull, ſtrong, and rich: which equality growes, by reaſon that they appropriate ſome one Staple Commodity to every Town of note: Onely <hi>Amſterdam</hi> not onely paſſeth them all, but even <hi>Sivil, Lisbone,</hi> or any Mart Towne in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome: And to it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated the Trade of the Eaſt Indies, where they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain commonly forty Ships;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115334:13"/>beſides which, there go twice a year from it and the adjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Townes, a great Fleete to the <hi>Baltique</hi> Sea: Upon the fall of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> that roſe rather then <hi>Meddleborough,</hi> though it ſtand at the ſame River's mouth, and is their ſecond Mart Towne, to which is appropriated our Engliſh Cloth.</p>
            <p>Concerning the people, they are neither much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout, nor much wicked; given all to Drink, and eminently to no other vice; hard in bargaining, but juſt, ſurly, and reſpectleſſe,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115334:13"/>as in all Democracies; thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, induſtrious, and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; diſheartned upon the leaſt ill ſucceſſe, and inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent upon good; inventive in Manufactures, cunning in Traffick; and general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for matter of Action, that naturall ſlowneſſe of theirs ſutes better, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that adviſedneſſe and perſeverance it brings with it, then the raſhneſſe and changeableneſſe of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Florentine</hi> Wits: and the equality of ſpirits which is among them and the <hi>Swiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers,</hi> renders them ſo fit for a Democracy; which kinde
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115334:14"/>of Government, Nations of more ſtable wits, being once come to a Conſiſtent Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, have ſeldome long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115334:14"/>
               <head>Obſervatoins on the State of the Arch-Dukes Countrey.</head>
               <p>AS ſoon as I entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Arch-Dukes Countrey (which begins after <hi>Lillow</hi>) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently I beheld works of a Province, and thoſe; of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince diſtreſſed with War; the people heartleſſe, and rather repining againſt their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, then revengfull againſt the Enemies, the bravery of that Gentry which was left,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115334:15"/>and the Induſtry of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant quite decayed; the Huſbandman labouring one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to live, without deſire to be rich to another's uſe; the Towns (whatſoever concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the ſtrength of them) ruinous: And to conclude, the people here growing poor with leſſe Taxes, then they flouriſh with, on the States ſide.</p>
               <p>This War hath kept the King of <hi>Spain</hi> buſie ever ſince it began; and ſpending all the Mony that the <hi>Indies,</hi> and all the Men that <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italie</hi> could afford, hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn him from perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115334:15"/>in any other Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize: Neither could hee give over this, without for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going the means to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take any thing hereafter upon <hi>France</hi> or <hi>England,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, the hope of the Weſterne Monarchie. For, without that handle, the Mines of <hi>Peru</hi> had done little hurt in theſe parts, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of what they have. The cauſe of the expenceful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, is the remoceneſſe of thoſe Provinces from <hi>Spain;</hi> by reaſon of which, every ſouldier of <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Italy,</hi> before hee can arrive there, coſts the King an hundred
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115334:16"/>Crowns, and not above one of ten that arrives, proves good: beſides, by reaſon of the diſtance, a great part of the Money is drunk up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Officers that convey it and pay it. The cauſe of the continuance of it, is, not onely the ſtrength of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but partly by reaſon that the Commanders themſelves are content the Warre ſhall laſt, ſo to maintain and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelves neceſſaries; and partly, becauſe the people of thoſe Countries are not ſo eager to have the other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, as willing to be in the like ſtate themſelves.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115334:16"/>
               <p>The uſuall Revenue of thoſe Provinces which the Arch-Duke hath, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to 1200000 Crowns a year; beſides which, there come from <hi>Spain</hi> every Month to maintain the War, 150000 Crowns. It was at the firſt, 300000 Crowns a month, but it fell by fifties to this, at the time when the Treaty began: <hi>Flanders</hi> payes more towards the warr then all the reſt, as <hi>Holland</hi> doth with the States. There is no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Spaniard</hi> of the Councell of State, nor Governour of any Province, but of the Councell of Warre, which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115334:17"/>is only active; There they only are, and have in their hands all the ſtrong Towns and Caſtles of thoſe Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of which the Governors have but only the Title.</p>
               <p>The Nations of which their Army conſiſts, are chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Italians,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulous one of another there; as on the other ſide, the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and of the Countrey, chiefly <hi>Burgundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and <hi>Wallons.</hi> The Popes Letters, and <hi>Spinola's</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination kept the <hi>Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> there, almoſt in equality of Command with the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> himſelf.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115334:17"/>
               <p>The Governours for the King of <hi>Spain</hi> there ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have been the Duke of <hi>Alva, Don Lewis de Requie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens, Don John d' Auſtria,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> the Arch-Duke <hi>Erneſtus,</hi> the Cardinall <hi>Andrew</hi> of <hi>Auſtrich,</hi> and the Cardinall <hi>Albert,</hi> till hee married the <hi>Infanta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where the Dominion of the Arch-Duke and the States part, there alſo changeth the nature of the Countrey, that is, about <hi>Antwerp:</hi> For all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low being flat, and betwixt Medow and Marſh, thence it begins to riſe and become Champion, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115334:18"/>the people are more quick and ſpiritfull, as the <hi>Braban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Flemming,</hi> and <hi>Wallon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt remarkable place in that ſide is <hi>Antwerp</hi> (which roſe upon the fall or <hi>Bruges</hi>) equally ſtrong and beautiful, remaining yet ſo upon the ſtrength of its former great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; twice ſpoyled by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and the like attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>French.</hi> The Cittadel was built there by the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> but renewed by the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> after his 18 months beſieging it; the Town accepting a Caſtle ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a Garriſon, to min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle among them. There are
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115334:18"/>yet in the Town of Citizens 30000 fighting men, 600 of which kept Watch nightly, but they allowed neither Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non upon the Rampier, nor Magazins of powder. In the Caſtle are 200 peeces of Ordnance, and commonly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or eight hundred Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. <hi>Flanders</hi> is the beſt of the ſeventeen Provinces, but the Havens therof are naught.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115334:19"/>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115334:19"/>
            <head>OBSERVATIONS On the State of FRANCE.</head>
            <p>Having ſeen the forme of a Common-Wealth and a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, with the different ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Warres in them, I entred <hi>France,</hi> flouriſhing with Peace, and of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies the moſt abſolute,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115334:20"/>becauſe the King there, not only makes Peace and Wars, Calls and diſſolves Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Pardoneth, natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizeth, Innobleth, Names the value of money, Preſſeth to the War; but even makes Laws, and impoſes Taxes at his pleaſure: And all this he doth alone: for as for that forme, that his Edicts muſt be authorized by the next Court of Parliament, that is, the next Court of Soveraign Juſtice; firſt, the Preſidents thereof are to be choſen by him, and to be put out by him; and ſecondly, when they concurre not with the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115334:20"/>King, he paſſeth any thing without them, as hee did the laſt Edict for the Proteſtants: And for the aſſembly of the three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, it is growne now almoſt as extraordinary as a generall Councell; with the loſſe of which their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty fell: and when occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on urgeth, it is poſſible for the King to procure, that all thoſe that ſhall be ſent thither ſhall be his Inſtruments: for the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> effected as much at the aſſembly of <hi>Bloys.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The occaſion that firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the King that Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115334:21"/>that his Edicts ſhould be Laws, was, the laſt Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> for at that time they poſſeſſing two parts of <hi>France,</hi> the three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates could not aſſemble; whereupon they did then grant that power unto <hi>Charls</hi> the Seventh during the War. And that which made it eaſie for <hi>Lewis</hi> the Eleventh and his Succeſſors to continue the ſame, the occaſion ceaſing, was, that the Clergy and Gentry did not run the ſame fortune with the people there, as in <hi>England;</hi> for moſt of the Taxes falling only upon the people, the Clergy and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115334:21"/>Gentrey being forborne, were eaſily induced to leave them to the Kings mercy. But the King having got ſtrength upon the Peaſants, hath been ſince the bolder to invade part of both their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>For the ſucceſſion of this Monarchy, it hath ſubſiſted without intermiſſion theſe 1200 years, under three Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Kings. No Nation hath heretofore done greater things abroad in <hi>Paleſtine</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> beſides all parts of <hi>Europe;</hi> but for theſe laſt forty yeares, they have onely made Sallies into <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115334:22"/>and often ſuffered at home.</p>
            <p>Three hundred years the <hi>Engliſh</hi> afflicted them, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king two firme Invaſions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and taking their King priſoner; the ſecond Greatneſſe of Chriſtendome, next the Emperour, being then in competition betwixt us and them; And to ſecure themſelves againſt us, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> as it then ſtood, they chuſe to marry the Heir of <hi>Bretaigne</hi> before that of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy.</hi> And for this laſt hundred yeares, the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard</hi> undertaking them,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115334:22"/>hath eaten them out of all but <hi>France,</hi> and endangered that too. But for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>France</hi> had never, as <hi>France,</hi> a more entire great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, though it hath often been richer. For ſince the Warre, the King is only got aforehand, the Countrey is but yet in recovering; the Warre having laſted by ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces 32 years; and ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, that no man but had an Enemy within three miles, and ſo the Country became Frontier all over. Now that which hath made them, at this time, ſo largely great at home, is their adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115334:23"/>into themſelves the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer adjoyning Nations, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deſtruction, or leaving any marke of ſtrangeneſſe upon them, as the <hi>Bretons, Gaſcoignes, Provincalls,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which are not <hi>French;</hi> towards the which Unions, their nature, which is eaſie and harborous to ſtrangers, hath done more then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Lawes could have ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, but with long time.</p>
            <p>The King (as I ſaid) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying what <hi>Lewis</hi> the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth did gaine, hath the entire Soveraignty in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, becauſe he can make
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115334:23"/>the Parliament do what he pleaſe, or elſe do what he pleaſe without them. For the other three Eſtates; The Church is there very rich, being eſtimated to enjoy the third part of the Revenue of <hi>France;</hi> but otherwiſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo potent as elſewhere, partly becauſe the Inquiſition is not admitted in <hi>France,</hi> but principally becauſe the Popes ordinary power is much reſtrayned there, by the Liberties which the <hi>French</hi> Church claymeth: Which Liberties do not ſo much enfranchize the Church it ſelfe, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115334:24"/>the Authority the Pope loſeth, upon the King, as firſt fruits, and the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of all Spirituall prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And by reaſon of this neutrality of Authority, the Church men ſuffer more there, then either in <hi>England,</hi> where they wholly depend upon the King; or in <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> where they wholly ſubſiſt by the Pope; becauſe the Pope is not able totally to ſupport them, and the King takes occaſion ever to ſuppreſſe them, as being not entirely his Subjects: and to him they pay yearely both the tenth of all their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115334:24"/>Tithe, and of all their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall land.</p>
            <p>The Gentrie are the onely entire Body there, which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate with the Prerogatives of the Crown; for from it they receive Priviledges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all other men, and a kind of limited Regality up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Tenants, beſides re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſupply to their eſtates, by Governments, and Penſions, and freedom from Tallies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own Lands; that is, upon their Demaines, and whatſoever elſe they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure by their Servants; but ſo much as they let to Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants is preſently Tallie-able,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115334:25"/>which cauſeth proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble abatement in the Rent; and in recompence of this, they owe the King the <hi>Ban</hi> and the <hi>Arriereban;</hi> that is, to ſerve him and his Lieutenant 3 Months within the Land at their owne charges. And as in Warre they undergo the greateſt part of the danger, then is their power perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptory above the reſt: wheras in time of Peace, the King is ready to ſupport inferiour perſons againſt them, and is glad to ſee them to waſte one another by contention in Law, for fear they grow rich; becauſe hee foreſees,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115334:25"/>that as the Nobility only can do him ſervice, ſo they only, miſapplyed, can doe him harme.</p>
            <p>The Ancient Gentrie of <hi>France</hi> was moſt of it conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Warres of <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> of <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> and ſome in thoſe of Saint <hi>Lewis,</hi> becauſe upon their ſetting out they pawned all their <hi>Feifs</hi> to the Church, and few of them were after redeemed; by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof the Church poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth at this day the third part of the beſt <hi>Feifs</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> and that Gentry was after made up by Advocates, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanciers, and Merchants in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobled,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115334:26"/>which now are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted antient, and are dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eaten out again, and repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the ſame kind of men.</p>
            <p>For the people; All thoſe that have any kinde of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion or Trade, live well; but for the meer Peaſants that labour the ground, they are onely Spunges to the King, to the Church, and the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, having nothing to their own, but to the uſe of them; and are ſcarce allowed (as Beaſts) enough to keep them able to do ſervice; for beſides their Rent, they pay uſually two thirds to the King.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:115334:26"/>
            <p>The manner of Government in <hi>France,</hi> is mixt, betwixt Peace and War, being compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as wel of Military Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, as Civil Juſtice, becauſe having open Frontiers and ſtrong neighbours, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obnoxious to ſudden In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions, they cannot (as in <hi>England</hi>) join ever Peace and ſecurity together.</p>
            <p>For the Military part, there is ever a Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and a Marſhall in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Troopes of Horſe, and Regiments of Foot in pay, and in all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces and places of ſtrength, Governors and Garriſons di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115334:27"/>all which are means for the preferment of the Gentry; But thoſe, as they give ſecurity againſt the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; ſo when there is none, they diſturbe the enjoying of Peace, by making the Countreys taſte ſomewhat of a Province. For the Gentry finde a difference betwixt the Governours fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and disfavour, and the ſouldiers commit of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Inſolencies upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>The Governments there are ſo well diſpoſed by the King; as no Governour hath means to give over a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115334:27"/>Province into the Enemies hand, the Commands there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are ſo ſcattered: for the Governour Commands the Countrey, and for the moſt part the chiefe Town; then is there a Lieutenant to the King, not to him, of the ſame, and betwixt theſe two there is ever Jealouſie nouriſhed; then hath eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Towne and Fortreſſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Governours, which are not ſubalterne to that of the Province, but hold imedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from the Prince; and many times the Town hath one Governor, and the Caſtle another.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:115334:28"/>
            <p>The advantages of Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours (beſides their pay from the King) are Preſents from the Country, dead payes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their Magazins of corn and powder more then they need, at the Kings price; and where they ſtand upon the Sea, overſeeing of unlawfull goods: Thus much in Peace. In Warre they are worth as much as they will exact. <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedoc,</hi> is the beſt, then <hi>Bretaign: Provence</hi> is worth, by all theſe means, to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> twenty thouſand Crownes a yeere: but <hi>Provence</hi> onely hee holds without a Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:115334:28"/>
            <p>Concerning the Civill Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice there, it is no where more Corrupt nor expence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. The Corruptneſſe of it proceeds, firſt by reaſon that the King ſels the places of Juſtice at as high a rate as can be honeſtly made of them; ſo that all thriving is left to Corruption; and the gain the King hath that wayes, tempts him to make a multitude of Officers, which is another burthen to the Subject. Secondly, the Preſidents are not bound to judge according to the written Law, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Equity drawne
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115334:29"/>out of it, which Liberty doth not ſo much admit Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as leave wit without limits. The expencefulneſs of it ariſeth from the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Lawes, and multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of formes of Proceſſes, the which two both beget doubt, and make them long m reſolving. And all this <hi>Chiquanerey,</hi> as they call it, is brought into <hi>France</hi> from <hi>Rome,</hi> upon the Popes co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to reſide at <hi>Avig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the ſtrength of <hi>France,</hi> It is at this day the greateſt united Force of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: The particulars in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115334:29"/>which it conſiſts are theſe; The ſhape of the Countrey, which being round, no one part is far from ſuccouring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; The multitude of good Townes and places of ſtrength therein are able to ſtay an Army, if not to waſte it, as <hi>Metz</hi> did the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; the maſſe of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which the King hath in the <hi>Baſtile;</hi> The number of Arſenalls diſtributed upon the Frontiers, beſides that of <hi>Paris,</hi> all which are full of good Armes and Artillery: And for ready men, the five Regiments beſtowed up and down in Garriſons, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115334:30"/>with the 2000 of the Guard; the Troopes of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and light Horſe, all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in pay; beſides their Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, all bred Souldiers, and of which they think there are at this preſent 50000 fit to bear Armes: And to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all theſe, they have at this day the beſt Generalls of Chriſtendom; which is the only commodity the Civill wars did leave them.</p>
            <p>The weakneſſes of it are, firſt the want of a ſufficient In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry, which proceeds from the ill diſtribution of their wealth; for the Peaſant, which containes the greateſt part of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115334:30"/>the people, having no ſhare allowed him, is heartleſſe and feeble, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unſerviceable for all Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary uſes; by reaſon of which, they are firſt forced to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row aide of the <hi>Swiſſers</hi> at a great Charge, and ſecondly to compoſe their Armies for the moſt part of Gentlemen, which makes the loſſe of a battaile there almoſt irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. The ſecond is the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionable part of the land which the Church holds, all which is likewiſe dead to military uſes. For as they ſay there, <hi>The Church will loſe nothing, nor defend nothing.</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115334:31"/>The third, is the want of a Competent number of Ships &amp; Gallies; by reaſon of which defect, firſft the <hi>Spaniard</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters them upon the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diterranian, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Hollander</hi> upon the Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. And ſecondly it renders them poor in forraign Trade, ſo that all the great actions of Chriſtendome for theſe fifty years, having been bent upon the <hi>Indies,</hi> they onely have ſate idle. The fourth is the weakneſſe of their Frontiers, which is ſo much the more dangerous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are poſſeſſed, all but the Ocean, by the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard:</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115334:31"/>for <hi>Savay</hi> hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways as his own for all uſes againſt <hi>France.</hi> The laſt is the difference of Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, which will ever yeild matter of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill diſſention, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently cauſe the weaker to ſtand in need of forraign ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours. The ordinary Revenue of the King, is, as they ſay now, ſome 14. Millions of Crowns, which ariſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally from the Demains of the Crowne, the gabell of Salt, tallies upon the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, Cuſtomes upon the Merchandize, ſale of Offices, the yearly Tithe of all that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115334:32"/>belongs to the Church, the riſing and falling of Money, Fines and Confiſcations caſt upon him by the Law; but Wardſhips, they are onely knowne in <hi>Normandy.</hi> His expence is chiefely Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, Munition, Building, Fortifying, and maintaining of Gallies, (As for Ships, when he needs them, hee makes an Embarke) In Pay for Souldiers; Wages for Officers, Penſions at home and abroad, upon the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining his Houſe, his State, and his private plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. And all the firſt, but the Demains, were granted
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115334:32"/>in the beginning, upon ſome urgent occaſion, and after by Kings made perpetuall, the ocaſion ceaſing; and the Demaines it ſelf granted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Kings ſhould live upon their own, without op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing their Subjects. But at this day, though the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue be thus great, and the taxes unſupportable, yet do they little more then ſerve for neceſſary publick uſes. For the King of <hi>Spain's</hi> great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Neighbourhood, forceth the King there to live continually upon his Guard; and the treaſure which the <hi>Spaniard</hi> receives from
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115334:33"/>his <hi>Indies,</hi> conſtraines him to raiſe his Revenue thus by Taxes, ſo to be able in ſome proportion to bear up againſt him, for feare elſe hee ſhould be bought out of all his Confederates and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
            <p>For the relation of this State to others, It is firſt to be conſidered, that this part of Chriſtendome is ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced betwixt the three Kings of <hi>Spain, France,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> as the other part betwixt the <hi>Ruſsian,</hi> the Kings of <hi>Poland, Sweden,</hi> and <hi>Denmarke.</hi> For as for <hi>Germany,</hi> which if it were entirely ſubject to one
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115334:33"/>Monarchy, would be terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all the reſt, ſo being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided betwixt ſo many Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and thoſe of ſo equall power, it ſerves only to bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance it ſelfe, and entertaine eaſie Warre with the <hi>Turke,</hi> while the <hi>Perſian</hi> with-holds him in a greater. And every one of thoſe firſt three hath his particular ſtrength, and his particular weakneſſe: <hi>Spaine</hi> hath the advantage of both the reſt in Treaſure, but is defective in Men, his Dominions are ſcattered, and the conveyance of his Treaſure from the <hi>Indies</hi> lyes obnoxious to the power of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115334:34"/>any Nation that is ſtronger by Sea. <hi>France</hi> abounds with Men, lyes cloſe together, and hath mony ſufficiently. <hi>England</hi> being an Iland, is hard to be Invaded, abounds with men, but wants money to imploy them. For their particular weakneſſe: <hi>Spain</hi> is to be kept buſie in the <hi>Low-Countreys: France</hi> is to bee afflicted with Proteſtants; and <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Ireland. Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is not able to ſubſiſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any of the other hand to hand; but joyned with the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi> it can give Law to both by Sea; and joyned with either of them
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115334:34"/>two, it is able to oppreſſe the third, as <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth did.</p>
            <p>Now the only entire body in Chriſtendome that makes head againſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, is <hi>France;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſay in <hi>France,</hi> that the day of the ruine of <hi>France,</hi> is the Eve of the ruine of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> And thereupon <hi>England</hi> hath ever ſince the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> greatneſſe, inclined rather to maintain <hi>France,</hi> then to ruine it; as when King <hi>Francis</hi> was taken priſoner, the King of <hi>England</hi> lent Money to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the payment of his Ranſome: And the late
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115334:35"/>Queen (when the Leaguers, after the of Duke <hi>Guiſe</hi> his death, had a deſigne to Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonize <hi>France</hi>) though offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a part, would not conſent. So then this reaſon of State, of mutuall preſervation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning them, <hi>England</hi> may be counted a ſure confederate of <hi>France;</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it partly ſubſiſts by it; the Proteſtant Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> becauſe they have Countenance from it againſt the houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant <hi>Swiſſers</hi> for Religion and Money; the <hi>Venetians</hi> for protection againſt the <hi>Spaniard</hi> in <hi>Italy:</hi> ſo that all
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115334:35"/>their friends are either Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, or en clining; and whoſoever is extream Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, is their enemy, and Factors for the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, as the Pope, the Cardinalls for the moſt part, and totally the Jeſuites, the hatholick Princes of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and the Catholicks of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> For the Jeſuites, which are the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſti call ſtrength of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, <hi>France,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the many late Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations, hath cauſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of them: for they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, as, one Pope, ſo one King, to ſuppreſſe the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115334:36"/>Proteſtants, and for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſupport of Chriſtendome againſt the <hi>Turke;</hi> and ſeeing <hi>Spaine</hi> the likelier to bring this to paſſe, they follow the neerer probability of effecting their end.</p>
            <p>No addition could make <hi>France</hi> ſo dangerous to us, as that of our <hi>Low-Countreys:</hi> for ſo it were worſe then if the <hi>Spaniard</hi> himſelfe had them entirely. As for their hopes of regaining <hi>Italy,</hi> it concerns the <hi>Spaniard</hi> immediately ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then us.</p>
            <p>Concerning the ſtate of the Proteſtants in <hi>France,</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Peace they are protected
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115334:36"/>by their Edict: For their two Agents at Court defend the Generall from wrong, and their <hi>Chambres-impartyes</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular perſon. And if troubles ſhould ariſe, ſome ſcattered particulars might be in danger, but the main body is ſafe, ſafe to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, though all <hi>France</hi> joyne againſt them: and if it break out into Factions, the ſafeſt, becauſe they are both ready and united.</p>
            <p>The particulars of their ſtrength are, firſt their Townes of ſurety, two of which command the River of <hi>Loyre.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:115334:37"/>
            <p>Secondly, their Situation, the greateſt part of them ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neer together, as <hi>Poictou, Zaingtongue,</hi> High <hi>Gaſcoigne, Languedoc,</hi> and <hi>Daulphine,</hi> neer the Sea; ſo conſequently fit to receive ſuccours from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad: and remote from <hi>Paris,</hi> ſo that the quality of an Army is much waſted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it can approach them.</p>
            <p>The third, is the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of their preſent Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, <hi>Bulloigne</hi> and <hi>Deſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiers,</hi> and other ſecond Commanders. And for the Princes of the Blood, whom the reſt may, in ſhew, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:115334:37"/>emulation obey, when they come once to open a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, thoſe which want a party will quickly ſeeke them.</p>
            <p>The laſt, is the aide they are ſure of from forraigne Princes; for whoſoever are friends to <hi>France</hi> in generall, are more particularly their friends.</p>
            <p>And beſides, the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant party being growne ſtronger of late, as the <hi>Low-Countreys;</hi> and more united, as <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> part of that ſtrength reflects upon them; and even the King of <hi>Spain</hi> himſelf, which is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:115334:38"/>to <hi>France</hi> in generall, would rather give them ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, then ſee them utterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpated: and yet no Forraign Prince can ever make fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſe of them, then to diſturbe <hi>France,</hi> not to invade it himſelf. For as ſoon as they get an Edict with better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, they turn head againſt him that now ſuccored them, as they did againſt us at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their number, they are not above the ſeventeenth or eighteenth part of the people, but of the Gentlemen there are 6000 of the Religion;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115334:38"/>but ſince the Peace they have increaſed in people, as prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally in <hi>Paris, Normandy,</hi> and <hi>Daulphine,</hi> but loſt in the Gentry; which loſſe comes to paſſe, by reaſon that the King when he finds any Gent. that wil but hearken, tempts him with preferment; and thoſe he finds utterly obſtinate, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth: And by ſuch means he hath done them more harm in Peace, then both his Predeceſſors in War. For in all their Aſſemblies he corrupts ſome of their Miniſters to betray their Counſel in hand; and of the hundred and ſixe thouſands Clowns a yeer,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115334:39"/>which he payes the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, to entertain their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and pay their Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, he hath gotten the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing of 16000 of them upon what Gentleman of the Religion hee pleaſeth, whom by that means he mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, if not gaines: and beſides, they were wont to impoſe upon him their two Deputies, which are to ſtay at Court; but now he makes them propoſe ſixe, out of which he chuſeth the two, and by that obligeth thoſe; and by notwithſtanding all this, in ſome occaſions hee makes good uſe of them too.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115334:39"/>For as towards <hi>England</hi> hee placeth none in any place of ſtrength but firme Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes; ſo towards <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Savoy</hi> hee often gives charge to Proteſtants, as <hi>la Force</hi> in <hi>Bearne, Deſdeguiers</hi> and <hi>Boiſſe</hi> in <hi>Breſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he is a perſon wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full both in Warre and Peace: for his Acts in Warre, he hath manumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed <hi>France</hi> from the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and ſubdued the League, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt dangerous plot that hath been laid; not weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it by Armes, but ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſſolving it by wit,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:115334:40"/>that is, by letting the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> out of Priſon, and Capitulating with the heads of it every one apart, by which means he hath ye left a continuall hatred among them, becauſe every one ſought, by preventing other, to make his Conditions the better; ſo that now there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans little connexion of it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Gentry; only there continues ſome dregges ſtill among the Prieſts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the people; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when they are angred with the increaſe proſperity of the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>For his Acts of Peace, he
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:115334:40"/>hath enriched <hi>France</hi> with a greater proportion of Wool, and Silk, erected goodly buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, cut Paſſages betwixt River and River, and is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to do the ſame betwixt Sea and Sea, redeemed much of the Mortgaged demains of the Crown, better husbanded the Mony, which was wont to be drunk up two parts of it in the Officers hands, got aforehand in Treaſure, Armes and Munition, increaſed the Infantry, and ſuppreſt the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionable Cavalry, and left nothing undone but the building of a Navy.</p>
            <p>And all this may be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:115334:41"/>to himſelf only, becauſe in a Monarchy, Officers are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly active or careleſſe, as the Prince is able to Judge and diſtinguiſh of their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and withall to partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate of them ſomewhat him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Sure it is, that the peace of <hi>France,</hi> and ſomwhat that of Chriſtendome it ſelf, is ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by this Princes life: For all Titles and Diſcontents, all fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Religion there ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs themſelves til his Death; but what will enſue after, what the reſt of the Houſe of <hi>Bourbon</hi> wil enterpriſe upon the Kings Children, what the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:115334:41"/>Houſe of <hi>Guiſe</hi> upon the houſe of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> what the League, what the Proteſtants, what the Kings of <hi>Spain</hi> &amp; <hi>England,</hi> if they ſee a breach made by civill Diſſention, I chuſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to expect then Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, becauſe God hath ſo many ways to turn aſide from humane foreſight, as he gave us a teſtimony upon the death of our late Queen.</p>
            <p>The Country of <hi>France,</hi> conſidering the quantity, is the faireſt and richeſt of all Chriſtendome, and contains in it moſt of the Countries ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning. For <hi>Picardie, Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,</hi> and <hi>Bretaign</hi> reſemble <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:115334:42"/>Languedoc, Spain; Provence, Italy;</hi> and the reſt is <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, all the Rivers that paſſe through it, end in it. It abounds with Corne, Wine, and Salt, and hath a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of Silke; but is defective in Wool, Leather, Metals, and Horſes; and hath but few ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Havens, eſpecially on the North ſide.</p>
            <p>Concerning the People; Their Children at firſt ſight ſeem men, and their men chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; but who ſo, in negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, preſumes upon appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſhall be deceived: Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate towards their own Nation and Country; loving
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115334:42"/>to the Prince; and ſo they may have liberty in Ceremony, and free acceſſe to him, they wil be the better content that he ſhall be abſolute in matter of Subſtance; impatient of peace any longer then whiles they are recovering the ruines of Warre; the preſentneſſe of danger inflames their corage, but any expectation makes it languiſh; for the moſt, they are all Imagination, and no Judgement; but thoſe that prove ſolid, excell. Their Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen are all good outward men, good Courtiers, good Souldiers; and knowing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in Men and Buſineſs;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:115334:43"/>but meerly ignorant in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Letters, becauſe at fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen they quit books, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to live in the world: when indeed, a mediocrity betwixt their form of education and ours, would do better then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. No men ſtand more punctually upon their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors in matter of Valour; and which is ſtrange, in nothing elſe: for otherwiſe in their Converſation, the Cuſtome, and ſhifting, and overſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, hath quite evercome the ſhame of it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:115334:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
